Preliminary Guide to the Harold Jantz Papers, 1500-1989 RL.00629
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harold Jantz papers
1500-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jantz, Harold Stein, 1907-1987
RL.00629
30.5 Linear Feet About 60,000 items
Noted professor of German literature and collector of German baroque literature. Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his FAUST, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive. Accession (2008-0159) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Harold Jantz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift, 1990-2008.
Biographical Note
Harold Jantz was a Professor of German literature at Northwestern, Johns Hopkins, and Duke Universities, and a collector of German baroque literature and German Americana.
Collection Overview
Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his FAUST, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive. Accession (2008-0159) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically.
Collection Arrangement
This collection has not been processed and therefore no arrangement has been completed at this time.
Related Material
The Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums, 1477-1905 is also housed at Duke University. The collection consists primarily of bound manuscripts, many illustrated, from the 15th through the early 20th centuries. Most materials are in German or English, with some materials in French, Hebrew, Italian, Spanish, Swedish, Greek, or Latin. In addition to the above noted subgroups, the collection includes medical texts; historical chronicles, mostly German; and alchemical/astrological/occult treatises. Among the identified authors are Georg Fabricius, Edward Young, Sebastian Chiesa, Henry Marchant, Jacob Böhme, J.M. Firmenich, and Carl and Julius Dresel. For more information, please see the collection's finding aid.
There is also a collection of graphic arts featuring prints collected by Jantz from Europe, America, and Asia.
Scrapbooks; Advertisements; Chromolithographs; German literature -- History and criticism; Pastorius, Francis Daniel, 1651-1719; Jantz, Harold Stein, 1907-1987; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Faust
- Harold Jantz Papers, 1500-1982, 67 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his Faust, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive (Box 32 of 1994-0001, Top of OC:IV).
  - Accession (1994-0001) (Box 1-33)
  - Accession (1996-0033) (Box 1-10)
  - Accession (1996-0097) (Box 1-20)
  - Accession (1998-0172) (Box 1-2)
  - Cards (Box 1-2)
- Accession (2008-0159), 1880-1985, 5 boxes
  Accession (2008-0159) (2625 items; 3.5 lin. ft; dated 1880-1985) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically. Most of the scrapbook's chromolithographs appear to be artwork promoting a particular brand or product.
  - Blue books (Box 1 (Acc. 08/159))
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 2-4 (Acc. 08/159))
  - Scrapbook of chromolithographs, 1880-1910 (Box 5 (Acc. 08/159))
- Accession (2010-0040), 1962-1980
  - Academics
    - Encyclopedia of Philosophy article, 1962 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Faust and the Faustian (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Wilhelm Meister notes, outline, and first book draft (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Mollhausen (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Cajutenbuch materials for a sequel. Introduction and notes (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Faust and Hamlet (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Literary criticism: The Uses of Poetry, etc. (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Literary criticism and history: notes and drafts (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - The Uses of Poetry drafts (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Literary history (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Goethe's Faust Intrinsically, Part Two (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - German views of the American Revolution (some recovered sources) (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - The Disengaged Individual: Mystic and Libertine in the 18th Century (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - DAAD directory (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Recommendation request: Eric Denton (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Recommendation request: G. Richard Dimler (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Recommendation request: Dick Zipser (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Recommendation request: Heinz Bluhm (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - The Form of Faust manuscript (folder 1 of 2) (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - The Form of Faust manuscript (folder 2 of 2) (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Scholastic and literary topics (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
  - Audiovisual materials, 1973; 1
    - Tape #1, Fall 1973, Faust, Dr. Jantz; Lectures 1-4, 1973 September 18-1973 October 9; 1
      - Original 1/4" audio tape (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL00629-RR-0001)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 1, Part 1, 1973 September 18 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0001)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 1, Part 2, 1973 September 18 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0002)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 2, Part 1, 1973 September 25 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0003)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 2, Part 2, 1973 September 25 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0004)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 3, Part 1, 1973 October 2 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0005)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 3, Part 2, 1973 October 2 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0006)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 4, Part 1, 1973 October 9 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0007)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 4, Part 2, 1973 October 9 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0008)
    - Tape #2, Fall 1973, Faust, Dr. Jantz; Lectures 5-8, 1973 October 16-1973 November 6; 2
      - Original 1/4" audio tape (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL00629-RR-0002)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 5, Part 1, 1973 October 16 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0009)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 5, Part 2, 1973 October 16 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0010)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 6, Part 1, 1973 October 23 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0011)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 6, Part 2, 1973 October 23 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0012)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 7, Part 1, 1973 October 30 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0013)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 7, Part 2, 1973 October 30 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0014)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 8, Part 1, 1973 November 6 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0015)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 8, Part 2, 1973 November 6 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0016)
    - Tape #3, Fall 1973, Faust, Dr. Jantz; Lectures 9-12, 1973 November 13-1973 December 4; 3
      - Original 1/4" audio tape (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL00629-RR-0003)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 9, Part 1, 1973 November 13 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0017)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 9, Part 2, 1973 November 13 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0018)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 10, Part 1, 1973 November 20 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0019)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 10, Part 2, 1973 November 20 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0020)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 11, Part 1, 1973 November 27 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0021)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 11, Part 2, 1973 November 27 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0022)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 12, Part 1, 1973 December 4 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0023)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 12, Part 2, 1973 December 4 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0024)
    - Tape #4, Fall 1973, Faust, Dr. Jantz; Lecture 13, 1973 December 11; 4
      - Original 1/4" audio tape (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL00629-RR-0004)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 13, Part 1, 1973 December 11 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0025)
      - Compact disc use copy, Lecture 13, Part 2, 1973 December 11 (Box AV1, Audio-disc RL00629-CD-0026)
  - Collections
    - Bibliography (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Book bills, 1960-1962 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Book bills, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Baroque inventory (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Duke collection inventory (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Americana in the Harold Jantz collection (folder 1 of 2) (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Americana in the Harold Jantz collection (folder 2 of 2) (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
  - Correspondence (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1 (Acc. 10/040))
- Accession (2011-1043), 1652?-1980s, 6 boxes
  Professional personal papers of Harold Jantz. Includes materials related to travel, his collecting, and academic correspondence. Also includes numerous drafts, notes (in exam blue books), and correspondence related to his research and writing about Goethe, Faust, German Americana, Baroque writings, and other topics.
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 1 (11/1043))
  - Correspondence (Box 2 (11/1043))
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts (Box 2 (11/1043))
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts (Box 3 (11/1043))
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts (Box 4 (11/1043))
  - Correspondence (Box 4 (11/1043))
  - Research files and photocopies (Box 4 (11/1043))
  - Administrative and professional papers re: German Department, university work (Box 4 (11/1043))
  - Correspondence (Box 5 (11/1043))
  - Research files (Box 5 (11/1043))
  - Miscellaneous materials relating to Austrian apartments (Box 6 (11/1043))
  - Printed and manuscript items (includes Accession 2004-0131), 1652?-1934 and undated; 0.2 Linear Feet (Box 7 (11/1043, 04/0131))
  - Oversize items (Oversize-folder 1 (11/1043))
- Accession (2014-0193), 1925-1928
  - University ephemera (Box 1 (14/0193))
  - Correspondence (Box 1 (14/0193))
  - University papers (Box 1 (14/0193))
- Accession (2018-00037), 1972-1989; 0.5 Linear Feet
  - Bibliographic and collection information, 1972-1988 (Box 1 (18/0037))
  - Journals, 1975-1989; 2 folders (Box 1 (18/0037))
  - Duke University Library correspondence, 1977 May 13 (Box 1 (18/0037))
  - German American Literary Relations Conference, 1979 March 22-24 (Box 1 (18/0037))